So today's דף daf is ט"ז Tet Zayin and we have now
moved on from the discussion about how a woman is acquired or
acquires herself and how a יבמה yevama which is a similar type
of a scenario and we've moved on to other acquisitions and this
is really the פרק perek about קניינים kinyanim and we so we
go down first between slowly we're getting to like you know inanimate
objects but still we're on people so we go from the קנין
kinyan of a woman which is marriage which as we've discussed might
have evolved from something that's more קנין kinyan based to something that's
more about you know about status based then we get to the
קנין kinyan related to a Jewish slave עבד עברי Eved Ivri which
is not owning the person as property but owning the rights to
their labor and then we're going to move on to עבד כנעני
Eved Knaani
which is owning the person as property although again the sort of
innovation of the תורה Torah is that the person even though the
slave even though property is also still recognized as a human being
and that's you know we'll get to that but that's like again
you know sadly something that wasn't a tremendous חידוש chiddush in the
ancient world and then we slowly move on to animals and then
finally to inanimate objects and so on. Okay so we're still here
people and people who are not really a full ownership עבד עברי
Eved Ivri which is owning them for their for their labor
מעשה ידיהם ma'asei yedeihem and how is that done? So the first
one mentioned in the משנה mishna was כסף kesef the גמרא Gemara
sort of figured out how we learn that it's interesting that one
of the basis of that might be you know the whole issue
about קידושין kiddushin again that comparison about קידושין kiddushin and עבדות avdut
and so on. Anyway different places that was learned from and now
we move on to שטר. shtar. So it's on ט"ז Tet Zayin
עמוד א' amud aleph five lines from the top ובשטר. uv'shtar. מנלן?
minalan? Where is this from? אמר עולא אמר קרא אם אחרת יקח
לו. Amar Ulla amar kra im acheres yikach lo. So this is
again this is by the אמה עברייה amah ivriyah and a father
sells his daughter as a slave and then there's the option of
marrying her. If the master marries her it says and then he
takes another wife שארה כסותה ועונתה לא יגרע. she'era kesuta ve'onata lo
yigra. He cannot minimize the rightly wifely due of the first one
even though the first one he might treat her in a you
know with less status. He originally she was a slave presumably she
came from the lower classes because you know the father sold her
into slavery the other woman maybe was a woman of his own
status and so on. The תורה Torah says even so you must
continue to treat the first wife with all of her due שארה
כסותה ועונתה she'era kesuta ve'onata the obligations that we learn out in
כתובות Ketubot the husband to wife and so on. Okay so what
do we have from that though? אם אחרת יקח לו? im acheres
yikach lo? הקישה הכתוב לאחרת. hekisha hakatuv leacheres. So it links the
acquisition of this woman as a slave when she was originally purchased
to now he's taking a wife. So we're going to make the
comparison of the sale of a girl as a slave to marriage.
מה אחרת מקניא בשטר ma acheres maknya b'shtar
the same way if he's marrying a woman as a wife the
second wife he can do it through a שטר shtar אף אמה
עברייה מקניא בשטר af amah ivriyah maknya b'shtar even an אמה עברייה.
amah ivriyah. Now of course the question is how do you know
that like maybe the second wife he married with כסף kesef maybe
the second wife he married with ביאה? biah? Okay although you could
say maybe the פסוק pasuk wouldn't have to tell me כסף kesef
I already know כסף. kesef. Anyway let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. הניחא למאן דאמר שטר אמה עברייה אדון כותבו. haniha leman d'amar
shtar amah ivriyah adon kotvo. If you say that the שטר shtar
for a Jewish slave for a for a girl
is the that the master writes it then it's a good comparison.
אלא למאן דאמר אב כותבו מאי איכא למימר? ela leman d'amar av
kotvo mai ika lemeimar? But if the father writes it what can
you say? Which means okay who is writing? I am purchasing Michael's
you know five year old daughter. How old is your daughter Michael?
Well my youngest one is eight.
Okay excellent we got four years of service from her. I am
purchasing Michael's eight year old daughter. Okay now do I write a
שטר shtar and say בתך קנויה לי bitcha knuya li okay
and give it to Michael? Or does Michael write a שטר shtar
and write בתי מכורה לך biti mechura lach and give it to
me?
So this is a general question right? Like if you buy my
car.
Right now when you write a שטר shtar for קרקע karka for
land the מוכר mocher writes it. It's שדי מכורה לך sadi mechura
lach the מוכר mocher writes it and then if you think about
it the reason is because if all a שטר shtar was was
some instrument to exact to effect the transaction then logically it could
go in either direction. But a שטר shtar also can serve and
often like would serve as proof. Who needs proof that the sale
took place? The purchaser not the seller. So so normally the person
selling the land writes שדי מכורה לך. sadi mechura lach.
So if that was the analogy here Michael would write to me
בתי מכורה לך. biti mechura lach. Okay
but if the comparison is to קידושין kiddushin by קידושין kiddushin it's
the man who writes הרי את מקודשת לי. harei at mekudeshet li.
So and if I were marrying Michael's daughter I would write הרי
בתך מקודשת לי. harei bitcha mekudeshet li.
So if I am buying Michael's daughter as a slave I'm going
to write הרי בתך קנויה לי. harei bitcha knuya li.
Just be sure to pay your tuition bills. A deal.
Okay.
Then I don't have to pay you anything. That's better than... anyway,
fine. Okay, so that's the question, which is a really good question,
right, which gets to this issue that we're learning it out from
marriage, right? So the marriage-slave comparison, but also if the slave is
of something that much more evokes sale of property and therefore it
would be the seller, not the buyer, that would do it. Oh
thanks, we have a little double stuff there. Oh my god, thank
you. Okay, so which way does it work? So if we're going
to say the basis of learning out קניין שטר kinyan shtar
by an עבד eved is learned from קידושי אישה, kidushei isha, that
only works if it's the same person writing the שטר. shtar. If
the master is writing the שטר shtar the same way the husband
writes the שטר קידושין. shtar kiddushin. But if it is the father
writing the שטר, shtar, which is more the model of normal sale
of property, then it obviously cannot be learned out from the area
from the category of a קידושי אישה. kidushei isha. So which is
it? So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
הניחא למאן דאמר שטר אמה אדם כותבו. Hania l'man d'amar shtar ama
adam kotvo. If the master writes it, then I get it, that's
comparable to קידושי אישה. kidushei isha. The husband writes the שטר, shtar,
the master who's taking the girl in writes the שטר. shtar. אלא
למאן דאמר אב כותבו, Ela l'man d'amar av kotvo, but if it's
the father who writes it because it's more like the sale of
property, מאי איכא למימר, mai ika l'meimar, then you cannot learn it
out from קידושי אישה, kidushei isha, it's clearly the model is the
sale of property model, not the קידושי אישה kidushei isha model. So
which is it? דאיתמר, D'itmar, now let's teach about this debate. שטר
אמה עברייה, Shtar ama ivriya, the שטר shtar for buying a Jewish
slave woman, מי כותבו, mi kotvo, who writes it? רב הונא אמר
אדם כותבו, Rav Huna amar adam kotvo, the master writes it. רב
חסדא אמר אב כותבו, Rav Chisda amar av kotvo, the father writes
it. So
הניחא לרב הונא, hania l'Rav Huna, according to רב הונא Rav Huna
that the master writes it, it's comparable to שטר
קידושין. shtar
kiddushin.
אלא לרב חסדא מאי איכא למימר, Ela l'Rav Chisda mai ika l'meimar,
but according to רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, what could you say? So
it's clearly more based on the idea of sale of property and
therefore it's not learned out from קידושי אישה. kidushei isha. So what
is the basis that עבד עברי eved ivri or אמה עברייה ama
ivriya is a שטר? shtar? So אמר רב אחא בר יעקב אמר
קרא, amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov amar kra, the verse says לא
תצא כצאת העבדים, lo tetzei k'tzait ha'avadim, that when the girl goes
free, she shall not go free like slaves go free. Now what
that means is, it's not just limited to the girl, the way
חז"ל Chazal understand the meaning of that פסוק pasuk is that a
non-Jewish slave, how does a non-Jewish slave go free? What's the classic
way in the תורה Torah that a non-Jewish slave goes free?
When you strike out an eye, right, when you poke out an
eye or knock out a tooth. Okay, that's the case when, because
otherwise the תורה Torah doesn't really discuss it, but the תורה Torah
basically talks about passing the slave down, doesn't talk about a non-Jewish
slave going free, about an עבד כנעני eved Kena'ani going free.
So the גמרא Gemara understands that when the תורה Torah says by
a Jewish slave, is this a slave girl, but the גמרא Gemara
understands that it doesn't matter slave, whether it's a man or a
woman, it says shall not go free like slaves go free means
they don't go free if the master knocks out an eye, they
do not... what?
How do you know it's עבד כנעני? eved Kena'ani? It could be
עבד עברי, eved ivri, but the
פסוק pasuk over there by... well we can talk about that, but
it's clear from... okay, let's just assume that for now, okay? So
but
you're right, it's a good question, anytime the תורה Torah talks about
עבד, eved, which type of עבד eved is it talking about? But
for now let's assume that. So the גמרא Gemara understands לא תצא
כצאת העבדים lo tetzei k'tzait ha'avadim means that Jewish slaves, עבד עברי
eved ivri or אמה עברייה, ama ivriya, do not go free when
if the master knocks out an eye. Now I just want to
pause for a moment and speak about the question that this seems
unjust, right? I mean, here you have like this terrible thing, loss
of an eye, and you know, if even a non-Jewish slave who's
fully owned goes free, like how could it be that a Jewish
slave should not go free on the basis of that? But there's
an important...
but the answer is, yes, it's true, they don't go free, but
what does happen as a result of the master knocking out the
eye? Can anybody imagine? You have to pay. So if you imagine
that the damages are quite substantial, they're so substantial that even somebody
who is owned in perpetuity, a non-Jewish slave goes out as a
result of it, so if this person is a Jewish slave, would
they rather save themselves three years of service and not get any
compensation for the eye, or would they rather continue their three years,
whatever's left of their service, three years, four years, five years, but
get the significant compensation for the eye? So the presumably that's the
explanation of why they don't, and once they get compensated for the
eye, they could use some of that money to buy back their
own freedom. Okay, but that's anyway so but that's the הלכה halacha
that לא תצא כצאת העבדים. lo tetzei k'tzait ha'avadim. Now what does
it have to do with the fact that an אמה עברייה ama
ivriya is purchased by a שטר? shtar? So the דרשה drasha is
the following: לא תצא כצאת העבדים
אבל נקנית היא כקניין עבדים. lo tetzei k'tzait ha'avadim aval nikneit hi
k'kinyan avadim. She doesn't go out like slaves go out, but she
gets purchased like slaves get purchased. ומה ניהו שטר, u'ma nihu shtar,
and one of the ways a slave, meaning a non-Jewish slave, an
עבד כנעני, eved Kena'ani, which is treated really like property, what is
the way that gets purchased? By a שטר. shtar. שטר shtar because
actually an עבד כנעני eved k'naani is purchased the same way land
is purchased: שטר, shtar, כסף, kesef, and חזקה. chazakah. Okay? Now, so
therefore, if the דרשה drasha is she doesn't go free like an
עבד כנעני eved k'naani but she gets—but she gets purchased like an
עבד כנעני, eved k'naani, כסף kesef we don't need to teach, since
that we already know from yesterday's stuff. So to teach me that
she's purchased with a שטר. shtar. But the גמרא Gemara says, well
wait, there's the third possibility. The גמרא Gemara says,
ואימא אבל נקנית היא כקנין עבדים ומאי ניהו חזקה, v'eima aval nikneis
hi k'kinyan avadim u'mai nihu chazakah, maybe purchased like a slave with
חזקה. chazakah. Okay, those are the three: כסף, kesef, שטר, shtar, and
חזקה. chazakah. כסף kesef we're not talking about, that we know. But
maybe it's telling me that you can purchase an אמה עבריה amah
ivriyah with חזקה. chazakah. Now what's חזקה? chazakah? So a חזקה chazakah
is a way of basically showing mastery over something, taking—you could say
it's taking possession, but it's taking possession through showing mastery. By land,
it is through actually, interestingly, it's by improving the land. It's about
let's say I basically go and I fix some breach in the
wall. Okay?
By—by a slave, it's by having the slave do a service to
me. If I basically get the slave to, I don't know, you
know, tie my shoe, put on my coat for me, or something
like that, that's the חזקה, chazakah, I've taken possession of them.
What? The collar? You know, like a slave—like a
slave—no, because you're right, I mean, so you're right, it—it—it's show—it's not
just showing mastery of any sign of mastery, it's showing mastery through
like, you know, through some type of an interaction with the object.
Now what's interesting is, is that why is it that by land,
there's actually a debate, what if by land rather than me improving
the land, I got something from the land? I did—you said go
buy your—I bought your whole land here, I went over to your
apple tree and I picked an apple. Okay? So you would think
that's logical, that's similar to having the slave serve me, right? So
it's interesting that that's not as obvious. There is a little bit
of a lack of symmetry there between the חזקה chazakah of the
slave and the חזקה chazakah of the land. I should say, by
the way, I should also mention, I think I mentioned at the
beginning, that you have כסף, kesef, שטר, shtar, and חזקה chazakah by
land, and כסף, kesef, שטר, shtar, and
חזקה chazakah by—by non—by—by עבד כנעני, eved k'naani, and you have כסף,
kesef, שטר, shtar, and ביאה, biah, right, by the case, by, you
know, by קידושי אשה. kiddushei ishah. So some want to say that
maybe that's similar in the sense of like whether it's mastery, you
know, some—whatever. So, you know, getting back to that whole קנין kinyan
model, is that some way of seeing—of showing mastery? Obviously, I'd rather
not look at ביאה biah that way, but it's worth pointing out
the, you know, the parallels. Yes?
Right? Exactly. Right.
Right, exactly. Exactly.
Like taking care of them and then
that—maybe the ביאה biah is an instance of improving.
Like you're giving her something.
Right, right. So you know you can make some of these—I understand,
those are interesting types of comparisons to make, right? Or you could
try to define it less about mastery and more about receiving benefit,
which again works by the slave and by the אשה, ishah, you
know, but it doesn't work exactly by the land. Anyway, what is
noticeable is although you have כסף, kesef, שטר, shtar, חזקה, chazakah, כסף,
kesef, שטר, shtar, חזקה, chazakah, and even by the case of the
woman, however we understand ביאה, biah, כסף, kesef, שטר, shtar, ביאה, biah,
by the עבד עברי, eved ivri, you only have כסף kesef and
שטר. shtar. You don't have a parallel to חזקה. chazakah. You only
have two, you don't have three. So we're going to see that
in a minute, but I guess I'll—I'll ruin the end for you
and I'll tell you that that probably is because that דווקא davka
to show that עבד עברי eved ivri is not about owning the
person as property, right? So if we assume that ביאה biah is
not seen—intended as a parallel to חזקה, chazakah, ביאה biah is about
the—just you know, the—the coming together of husband and wife, you know,
the fundamental like, you know, partnership that is created through the marriage
and the intimacy, then we do not see that parallel. Then what
we have—what we have limited to is an idea of חזקה chazakah
is a full sense of possession. To possess is to totally like
take, you know, control over that object. And that does not exist
by עבד עברי. eved ivri. עבד עברי eved ivri you have rights
to their labor, but we don't have—which you know, you can understand,
you buy the rights with money, you can understand that you write
a שטר shtar that shows that you're entitled to those rights and
so on, it's a type of a contract, but we don't have
חזקה, chazakah, which is much more about possession. But the question is
how do we know that? If we're making a comparison to עבד
כנעני, eved k'naani, how do we know to say it means yes
שטר shtar but no חזקה? chazakah? Let's just see the answer. Okay.
ואימא, v'eima, let's say, אבל נקנית היא כקנין עבדים ומאי ניהו חזקה,
aval nikneis hi k'kinyan avadim u'mai nihu chazakah, maybe she should be
acquired with חזקה? chazakah? No, אמר קרא והתנחלתם אותם לבניכם אחריכם. amar
kra v'hisnachaltem osam livneichem achareichem. This is by עבד כנעני. eved k'naani.
You should bequeath them to your children after you, which again really
underscores them as property where they're bequeathed to the next generation. Okay.
אותם בחזקה ולא אחר בחזקה. osam b'chazakah v'lo acher b'chazakah. They are
with חזקה chazakah and not something else. Now again, where do you
see חזקה chazakah there? But רש״י Rashi exactly makes this point. If
you look at רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi says, והתנחלתם אותם, v'hisnachaltem osam,
it's about ten lines down in the narrow lines, רש״י Rashi says,
בעבד כנעני אכתיב
אותם כאחוזה, b'eved k'naani achsiv osam k'achuzah, like—right—you—like—it says והתנחלתם אותם לבניכם
אחריכם לרשת אחוזה. v'hisnachaltem osam livneichem achareichem lareshes achuzah. Right, that's—I think
the—the end of the פסוק. pasuk. So there on אחוזה... achuzah... A
possession, okay,
so הנקנים בחזקה ולא אחר. haniknim behazakah velo acher. So רש''י Rashi
really underscores the idea. No slave, עבד כנעני Eved Kena'ani is like
a possession and therefore חזקה, hazakah, which is about taking possession of
them, owning it as property, and therefore that's limited to עבד כנעני.
Eved Kena'ani. Okay, so we know that אמה עבריה Amah Ivriyah is
to some degree linked to slaves, and for that we say it
means שטר, shtar, but דוקא davka we're excluding חזקה, hazakah, which is
the קניין kinyan that really sort of identifies the object as property
and the person as full owner,
full possessor of that property. Yes, Michael, you had a question?
Yes, but with אמה עבריה, Amah Ivriyah, didn't we just say that
let's say he decides to marry her, he doesn't need other קידושין?
kiddushin? Right, כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin, but let's
say, but a שטר, shtar, one of the other ways of doing
it is with a שטר. shtar.
Oh, that's a good question, which is, that's an excellent question. Since
we say by אמה עבריה Amah Ivriyah if he wants to marry
her, the whole point is about the ability to marry her. We
learned before, if there's not an ability to marry her, you can't
sell her. They can't sell her to a relative, for example. And
we say that the כסף מכירה kesef mechira becomes כסף קידושין. kesef
kiddushin. What happens if she's sold by a שטר? shtar?
My guess would be that even if the act, you see, there's
always two questions, which is what is the act that effects the
transaction and
but if when you sell to me קרקע karka with a שטר,
shtar, the שטר shtar could effect the transaction, I still have to
pay you the money that I owe you. So there's going to
be money that changes hands, but your question is, but let's say
that money doesn't change hands till later, like I'll owe you the
money for it, right? And you don't pay me, so for the
first year where you have yet to have paid me for my
daughter there, there's no כסף kesef to do ייעוד yi'ud with. So
it's a good question. Meaning I would have said it's the money
of payment even if it's not the money that did the קניין,
kinyan, but the money of payment might not be right away. So
that's a really good question.
But then also then, do you need to write a new שטר
shtar that you decide, I know you write a כתובה, ketubah, but
then what do you מקדש mekadesh exactly? What do you מקדש? mekadesh?
No, no, you'd have to be מקדש, mekadesh, oh no, it would
not be that the שטר מכירה shtar mechira becomes a שטר shtar
because a שטר מכירה shtar mechira is too specific. It's the reason
that the כסף kesef the money can change its identity is because,
as the גמרא Gemara says, like, טיבעא חד הוא, tiva chad hu,
like money is money, it doesn't have an identity the way שטר
shtar does. It's a really good question and I'll have to check
into that, right? Because money will change hands, but it might not
have changed hands yet. So that's a really good point. The other
I think important question to ask here is can you use a
שטר מכירה shtar mechira if you're not having somebody else sell you?
If somebody is selling themselves, if an עבד עברי Eved Ivri is
selling himself, presumably yes. Like the משנה Mishnah just said עבד עברי
Eved Ivri is
בשטר, bishtar, but it's a little different, right? If it's a שטר,
shtar, if I'm selling myself, I would basically say like, אני מכור
לך, ani machur lecha, or if the person or if the other
that writes the שטר, shtar, he would write, אתה קנוי לי ata
kanuy li or something. It's a little funny, right? But you become
both the seller and as it were the object of the sale.
And presumably, it's easier to see that as the model of the
father and the daughter, but they can get conflated into one person
when we have you selling yourself. Okay, let's continue now. Okay,
ואין בה, ve'ein bah, we did that. Okay, ומה ראית, umah ra'ita,
okay, wait a minute, ואימא אותם בשטר ולא אחר, ve'eima otam bishtar
velo acher,
I'm sorry, did I skip a line? ומה ראית, umah ra'ita, אימא
קרא והתנחלתם אותם לבניכם אחריכם, eima k'ra vehitnachaltem otam livnechem achareichem, אותם
בחזקה ולא אחר בחזקה. otam behazakah velo acher behazakah. ואימא אותם בשטר
ולא אחר בשטר. ve'eima otam bishtar velo acher bishtar. Oh yeah, I
already sort of discussed this. Let's say maybe no, maybe the point
is that you don't sell, that slaves, עבד כנעני Eved Kena'ani is
with a שטר shtar but not עבד עברי. Eved Ivri. Flip it.
עבד עברי Eved Ivri is with חזקה hazakah and not a שטר.
shtar. So the גמרא Gemara says no, הכתיב לא תצא כצאת העבדים.
haktiv lo tetzei ketzeit ha'avadim. No, because we learn from לא תצא
כצאת העבדים lo tetzei ketzeit ha'avadim that it does have one way
in which it's parallel to an עבד
כנעני. Eved Kena'ani.
ומה ראית? umah ra'ita? So okay, why did you say it's parallel
that it's with a שטר shtar and the difference is not חזקה?
hazakah? Maybe we should say the reverse. What made you make the
split that way? מסתברא mistavra
שטר הוה ליה לרבויי. shtar havei lei leribuyei. It makes sense that
a שטר, shtar, of the two, שטר shtar and חזקה, hazakah, שטר
shtar should be the one that works by עבד עברי. Eved Ivri.
Why? שכן מוציא בבת ישראל. sheken motzi bebat Yisrael. Because we have
a שטר shtar working by Jews, things around sort of transactions around
a Jew as a where the transaction
where the person is sort of the object of the transaction. Where
do you have it? You have it by קידושין. kiddushin. Now תוספות
Tosafot says it actually is strange that it mentions גירושין. geirushin. It
says מוציא בבת ישראל. motzi bebat Yisrael. Why didn't it say מכניס
בבת ישראל machnisa bebat Yisrael which is a more parallel,
the husband as it were takes possession, obviously that's the קניין kinyan
model and therefore that's the same parallel. Why does it say מוציא?
motzi? So תוספות Tosafot says yeah, but it's just cause in the
תורה Torah it's more explicit of a שטר shtar by גיטין gittin
is explicit. The שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin is less explicit. But the
point is is that again here we're talking about a human being
and a type of a קניין kinyan around a human being. So
we're going to look, that's an unusual reality, and by a and
so we're going to look for another model for that, and we
want to look specifically amongst sort of not the עבד כנעני, Eved
Knaani, which is recognized as property, but a model amongst that amongst
like, you know, other types of קניינים kinyanim by Jews. Okay? So
therefore it says, well, you don't have חזקה chazakah ever working on
another person when you're not dealing with עבד כנעני. Eved Knaani. But
you do have שטר shtar working. So even though there's status aspects,
there's קנין kinyan aspects, so if you have שטר shtar working, it
makes sense that of the two, we'll say שטר shtar is what
works by עבד עברי Eved Ivri rather than חזקה. chazakah. So the
גמרא Gemara says אדרבה חזקה הויא ליה
לרבויי—no, aderaba chazakah havei lei leribuyei
I could say the opposite. חזקה chazakah should be the one that
should work by עבד עברי, Eved Ivri, not שטר. shtar. Why? שכן
קונה בנכסי הגר. sheken koneh be’nichsei hager.
Because a חזקה chazakah works in places where שטר shtar doesn't work.
Where does חזקה chazakah work where שטר shtar doesn't? A convert dies
and he has no children, so and he has no relatives, because
it's כתינוק שנולד, k’tinok shenolad, I mean כקטן
שנולד, kekatan shenolad, so his property is הפקר. hefker. So how do
you take possession when there's no seller of land? Okay, so you
can't do שטר shtar and you can't do כסף, kesef, but what
you can do is חזקה. chazakah. Okay, so we have a place
where חזקה chazakah works that שטר shtar doesn't. So maybe חזקה chazakah
is the more powerful קנין kinyan and it should work by עבד
עברי. Eved Ivri. So the גמרא Gemara says no, באשה מיהא לא
אשכחן, be’ishah miha lo ashkechan, but we've never found it by cases
of marriage. Now the funny thing is, but who's talking about marriage?
We're talking about עבד עברי, Eved Ivri, right? So, right, the גמרא
Gemara says like if we have to choose, we know an אמה
עבריה Amah Ivriyah is acquired either with חזקה chazakah or with שטר.
shtar. One of those two. One of them is like an עבד
כנעני. Eved Knaani. Which one? So חזקה chazakah is powerful in some
situations where שטר shtar is not. Maybe we'll go with חזקה. chazakah.
No, no, no. We'd rather learn out שטר shtar because שטר shtar
works in cases of אישות. ishut. Now why is that relevant for
עבד עברי? Eved Ivri? So you could say one of two things.
You could say well, it's relevant to אמה עבריה Amah Ivriyah because
אמה עבריה Amah Ivriyah can transform into a case of marriage. Okay,
but what I would also like to say is what I've been
saying, because you know, you know that it works by cases of
like personal status, of people, of human beings. So we'd rather use
a קנין kinyan of שטר shtar that we find works about human
beings rather than something about חזקה, chazakah, I mean that basically works
about only in regards to property. It does work by עבד כנעני,
Eved Knaani, but that's because עבד כנעני Eved Knaani is treated as
property. Okay, so that's of the two, we're going to pick שטר.
shtar. Okay, so there we have it. Okay, איבעית אימא, iba’it eima,
and if you want I could say, להכי אהני אם אחרת. lehachi
ahani im acheret. Now that's the combination of the two. That the
אם אחרת יקח לו, im acheret yikach lo, right, we said that
that teaches it—going back, remember at the beginning—it says אם אחרת יקח
לו im acheret yikach lo that the קנין kinyan of an אמה
עבריה Amah Ivriyah is like קנין kinyan of a woman, is like
קנין קידושין, kinyan Kiddushin, right? Remember about at the beginning? So the
only question was, well, that's not a good comparison if the different
party writes the שטר. shtar. So we say okay, maybe it wouldn't
have worked by itself, but in combination with this other לימוד limud
that says that one of the קניינים kinyanim of שלח shalleach works
by אמה עבריה, Amah Ivriyah, we're going to say אם אחרת—I im
acheret have a feeling that I'm losing everybody. I'm probably losing myself.
I right, I understand, you got it Michael, but let me just
here explain this, okay?
All
right.
So basically we have the idea of אם אחרת יקח לו, im
acheret yikach lo, which basically tells me that it's like that it's
קונה koneh עבד
עברי Eved Ivri or
אמה
עבריה
Amah
Ivriyah is a קנין, kinyan, the קנין kinyan is like is like
קידושין. Kiddushin. Okay, some קנין kinyan like קידושין. Kiddushin. Okay, that's what
we learned. אם אחרת יקח לו, im acheret yikach lo, it's the
same type of a קנין kinyan of קידושין Kiddushin can work for
אמה עבריה. Amah Ivriyah. Okay, which means we don't need to know
כסף. kesef. Obviously it's not ביאה. biah. So we're left with שטר.
shtar. Okay, that's how the גמרא Gemara first wanted to say שטר.
shtar. Okay, but then it said one minute. That depends who's writing
it. There's two models. Okay, here's the father and his daughter. Okay,
and here is the person buying it. Who's writing the שטר? shtar?
So there's two possibilities. One is he writes בתי קנויה לך.
biti
knuyah lach. Okay, the other one is that he writes, right, בתי
מכורה לך. biti mechurah lach. Let's do that. מכורה לך. mechurah lach.
Okay, and בתך קנויה לי. bit’cha knuyah li. Okay, two types of
שטרות shtarot that could be written, right? Okay, this, this model is
a שטר מכירה. shtar mechira. The seller writes a שטר shtar when
he's selling land. This model, בתך קנויה לי, bit’cha knuyah li, where
the one taking the woman is, this model is a שטר קידושין.
shtar Kiddushin. Okay, so if we learn out a שטר shtar from
אם אחרת יקח לו, im acheret yikach lo, that works with the
שטר קידושין shtar Kiddushin model, if you say that it's the master
that's writing it. Okay, because then it's similar to him taking possession
of a wife, קנין kinyan of a wife. If it's the father
writing it, and if it's learned it's more like the field model,
then this doesn't learn it out. So where we're going to learn
it out from is not here, but we're going to learn it
out from לא תצא כצאת
העבדים
lo tetzei k'tzeit
ha-avadim but נקנית כקניין עבדים, nikneis k'kinyan avadim, okay? So that's how
we're going to learn it out from. And this is עבד כנעני,
Eved Knaani, and עבד כנעני Eved Knaani is like basically is like
property, okay? So here the possession of like property by the עבד
כנעני Eved Knaani is a שטר, shtar, which is a שטר shtar
of buying property, okay? That was the—that was the second approach. But
then the question was one
minuto: maybe—maybe the קניין kinyan that you're telling me works here is
not שטר shtar but is חזקה. chazakah. Why do you prefer to
say that the קניין kinyan that works is שטר shtar and not
the קניין kinyan of חזקה? chazakah? So the גמרא Gemara has two
answers. One answer is שטר shtar is the better קניין kinyan for
עבד עברי Eved Ivri because it works—the way I'll interpret the גמרא—it
Gemara works on people, it works on a person who's not being
treated fully as property. חזקה chazakah only works on property and people
that are being treated fully as property. שטר, shtar, like we know
by קידושין kiddushin and גירושין, geirushin, works even on people who are
not being treated as property. So that's the one we'd rather apply.
And the other answer is: look, we already had from here the
idea that a שטר shtar would work. The only problem was it
wasn't an exact comparison, okay? Because the שטר shtar by אישות ishos
was he was writing and the שטר shtar here is that the
father is writing. But it basically was pointing in that direction that
שטר shtar would work, but we couldn't really fully learn it from
here because the comparison wasn't complete. But once we also have this,
then this is going to tell me that of these two, it's
the שטר shtar that's going to be the one that works and
not the חזקה. chazakah. So that's how they like work in concert.
Yeah, that—that one's a שטר מכירה. shtar mechira.
That's a classic שטר מכירה shtar mechira because that's talking about עבד
כנעני, Eved Knaani, okay? So this is a שטר מכירה shtar mechira
that the seller writes, okay? So I really would have wanted to
learn it here, but it would have pointed—but it would have given
me the wrong type of שטר. shtar. But once this tells me
that it's either שטר shtar or חזקה, chazakah, this is going to
tell me to pick שטר. shtar. Okay, at the bottom line, the
end of the day, what I think is significant is that it
is that you don't have the three: כסף, kesef, שטר, shtar, and
חזקה. chazakah. You only have כסף kesef and שטר. shtar. I think
that's exactly the point the גמרא Gemara is making here, that חזקה
chazakah is about possessing something that's property or as property, and that's
not the case here by עבד עברי. Eved Ivri.
Okay, so—that's the property example, but of the
two—yes, so it is true that it is learned from property, we're
going to pick—yes, right, so it has elements of property, but of
the two we're going to pick שטר shtar and not חזקה, chazakah,
because חזקה chazakah is only when something is treated as property, whereas
a שטר shtar has elements like by אישות, ishos, קידושין, kiddushin, and
גט, get, etc., which extend beyond the simple property model, right? So
that's the better one to use for עבד עברי. Eved Ivri.
A בוגרת bogeret can't be an אמה עברייה amah ivriyah or can?
Like once—a בוגר—no, boger cannot. Sorry,
but what—so it's a little bit—בין עברי כנעני, bein Ivri Knaani, can
someone sell himself into עבדות avdus כנעני? Knaani?
Yes, עבדות—no, avdus a non-Jew? Yes, I believe so, yeah.
So some ways it's a little bit not parallel to make any
of these comparisons to אמה עברייה amah ivriyah because she's sold by
somebody else, you know, whereas an עבד עברי Eved Ivri can sell
himself. Yeah.
I mean, you mean how do we know that—wait, are you asking
כנעני Knaani or עבד עברי? Eved Ivri? How do we know that
a קניין kinyan that works by אמה עברייה amah ivriyah where the
father is selling works by עבד עברי Eved Ivri where the person
is selling himself? That's your question? Yeah, that is a good question.
The גמרא's Gemara assuming that. That's also why I pointed that out.
I said it's funny that a שטר—it's shtar one thing for me
to write a שטר shtar and the seller is not the same
as the object that's being sold. It's very—it's weird, a little weird,
when the person is both the subject selling and writing the שטר
shtar or receiving the שטר, shtar, but the גמרא Gemara does assume
that. Okay, let's continue. רב הונא, Rav Huna, לא תצא כצאת העבדים
lo tetzei k'tzeit ha-avadim מאי דריש ביה? mai darish beih? So רב
הונא, Rav Huna, that already learns that אמה עברייה amah ivriyah is
with a שטר shtar and it's like קידושין, kiddushin, it's the master
writes it. What does he need לא תצא כצאת העבדים? lo tetzei
k'tzeit ha-avadim? You don't need it to teach me that there's a
קניין kinyan that works like a קניין kinyan of עבדים. avadim. So
the גמרא Gemara says: No, ההוא מיבעיא ליה hahu mibaya leih שאינו
יוצא בראש איברים כעבד, she'eino yotzei b'rosh evarim k'eved, to tell me
more פשט pshat in the פסוקים, psukim, or what חז"ל Chazal understand
as פשט: pshat: that she doesn't go free like an עבד כנעני,
Eved Knaani, or you know, an עבד עברי Eved Ivri does not
go free if a limb is—an eye is poked out or you
know a limb is cut off or whatever. רב חסדא, Rav Chisda,
אם כן, im kein, he would obviously agree that that's the basic
sense of the פסוק, pasuk, but אם כן im kein ליכתוב קרא
likhtov kra לא תצא כעבדים, lo tetzei k'avadim, don't go out like
slaves. מאי mai כצאת העבדים? k'tzeit ha-avadim? So why did it say
'like slaves go out'? It's an extra word. שמע מינה תרתי, shma
mina tarti, two things. Number one is doesn't go out if an
eye is poked out, and number two is doesn't go out—that the
going out isn't like slaves, but the coming in is like עבד
כנעני Eved Knaani and is with a שטר. shtar. Okay, so that's
how we know that עבד עברי Eved Ivri and yes Michael is
correct that we jumped from, you know, a father selling his underage
daughter and we assume the same is true about a man— person
selling himself. Okay, so that's how we know about עבד עברי Eved
Ivri is כסף Kessef and שטר, Shtar, and I have to get
back, Michael asked a very good question about if it's with a
שטר, Shtar, how does that work with ייעוד yi'ud by the case
of the girl, of the קטנה. ktana. Okay, וקונה עצמו v'koneh atzmo
בשנים b'shanim and gains his own freedom. What's the... let's just say
the משנה. mishna. A slave gains his freedom בשנים b'shanim after six
years of servitude, ביובל b'yovel if the יובל yovel comes in the
middle of those six years, וגירעון כסף u'gir'on kessef and with paying
back the remainder of the purchase price. So you're entitled, even if
the master doesn't want to agree to it, you have the right
to buy back your freedom by doing the pro-rated purchase price. Okay,
so let's go through those. בשנים b'shanim
דכתיב d'chtiv שש שנים יעבוד ובשביעית יצא לחפשי חינם. Shesh shanim ya'avod
u'vashvi'it yetzei lachofshi chinam. That's pretty clear. ביובל b'yovel דכתיב d'chtiv עד
שנת היובל יעבוד עמך. ad shnat hayovel ya'avod imach. Okay, and so...
and if that works by somebody who's let's say a נרצע, nirtza,
right, which is what we assume, somebody who did the whole poking...
you know, the hole in the ear, and it goes for even
by יובל, yovel, then certainly somebody who's only working for less time,
for six years. And וגירעון... u'gir'on... although we'll look at that in
a minute... וגירעון כסף u'gir'on kessef and the deducting of the money,
meaning paying back from the pro-rated purchase price. So אמר חזקיה אמר
קרא, amar Chizkiyah amar kra, the verse says והפדה, v'hefeda, right, it
says by the אמה עבריה. amah Ivriyah. It says, what does it
say? What's the פסוק pasuk by the
אמה עבריה? amah Ivriyah? לעם נכרי לא ימשל למכרה בבגדו בה. l'am
nochri lo yimshal l'mochrah b'vigdo bah. What is it? Yeah, אם רעה
בעיני אדוניה אשר לא ייעדה והפדה, im ra'ah b'einei adoneha asher lo
ye'adah v'hefeda, that he did not do ייעוד yi'ud והפדה. v'hefeda. As
we understand, and also what was not done was she was not
redeemed. So that shows you that redemption is a possible... is a
possible option. והפדה v'hefeda מלמד שמגרע פדיונה ויוצאה. melamed she'magre'a pidyonah v'yotzah.
That teaches you that you can deduct and do a pro-rated... exactly
how you know pro-rated from that, you know, is not exactly clear,
though רש"י Rashi says like והפדה v'hefeda means like she somehow is
an active participant in the redemption, which means that somehow her service
deducts from the amount of the cost of the redemption money. Okay,
so you pay back the pro-rated purchase price ויוצאה v'yotzah and she
can go free. So those are the three of the משנה. mishna.
Okay, תנא, tana, now we taught in a ברייתא braita more than
is in the
משנה. mishna. וקונה עצמו בכסף ובשוה כסף. v'koneh atzmo b'kessef u'v'shaveh kessef.
First of all, it's not just money, but even the equivalent of
money. That's another point. Okay, that's... that's פדיון, pidyon, but פדיון pidyon
can be even with, you know, not just cash.
ובשוה ובשוה כסף u'v'shaveh u'v'shaveh kessef ובשטר. u'v'shtar. But a new thing
also added is a שטר. shtar. So the גמרא Gemara says, בשלמא
כסף דכתיב bishlama kessef d'chtiv money it says, מכסף מקנתו. mikessef miknato.
That's how we learn... and that's another source of the basis that
somebody can buy back their freedom. Okay, it says over there in
ויקרא, Vayikra, which is the other case, that's the case about somebody
selling themselves as slaves. It says that, you know, that they're redeemed
from the money of their... from their purchase money. So that's another
source that somebody can buy back their freedom with the... you know,
based... you know, by paying back the purchase money from the money
of their purchase. שוה כסף נמי, shaveh kessef nami, how do we
know even if it's not cash? Because it says ישיב גאולתו yashiv
geulato in that same פרשה, parsha, it says should give... pay back
the redemption money. So the general... generic ישיב yashiv without it mentioning
כסף, kessef, cash, silver, right, that shows you that any form of
paying back the purchase price. So you can...
meaning, but I can also buy... ובשוה כסף?
u'v'shaveh kessef? Yeah. Okay. אמר רחמנא, amar Rachmana, so okay, לרבות שוה
כסף ככסף. l'rabot shaveh kessef k'kessef. So okay, the one thing the
ברייתא braita adds is שוה כסף, shaveh kessef, we get what... where
that's coming from the פסוק pasuk and along the way by the
way we added another source for the idea of פדיון, pidyon, not
והפדה, v'hefeda, but the פרשה parsha over there in בהר בחוקותי Behar
Bechukotai about... about a person who sells himself and then buying back
his freedom. אלא האי שטר היכי דמי? ela hai shtar heichi dami?
But how... where do we know that a שטר shtar is from...
it works? Or what's the scenario of the שטר? shtar? אילימא דכתב
ליה שטרא אדמי, eileima d'chtav lei shtar'a adamei, if the עבד eved
basically wrote an IOU to the master and that was a way
he bought back his freedom, היינו כסף, hainu kessef, that's money. Now
I have to tell you... I just want to pause here for
a moment, that that's not at all obvious that that should work.
That's not שוה כסף, shaveh kessef, right? An IOU a thousand dollars
is just a... you know, it's not... there's no intrinsic value to
the IOU, it's just saying I have this debt, but no object
of value ever changed hands. Right? Now I guess what you could
say is, it's like the master says, let it be like you've
paid me back and now I've lent you the money. Right? So
like imagine that that's what happened and therefore it's as if you
paid me back. So I understand how it could work, but I
wouldn't say פשיטא p'shita that it works. There's a חידוש chidush that
no money changed hands and he buys back his freedom. One minute.
So okay, היינו כסף, hainu kessef, the גמרא Gemara says.
אלא שחרור, ela shichrur, so rather, so the case of שטר shtar
that we must be talking is that the master writes a שטר
shtar and he says הרי את harei at הרי אתה בן חורין,
Harey ata ben khorin, because we're going to see that that works
by עבד כנעני. eved K'naani. So maybe that's what we're saying, that
that works. So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, if that's what
we're, that's the שטר shtar that works, so שטר למה לי? shtar
lamma li? Why do you need a שטר? shtar? למה לה באפי
תרי: זיל! Lema leh be-appei terei: Zil! Go say in front of
two people, witnesses, go, you're free, I renounce my claim to you.
אינמי באפי בי דינא: זיל! Inami be-appei bei dina: Zil! Or say
in front of a בית דין, beis din, I renounce my claim
to you. Now this is very important. Note, the גמרא Gemara right
now is not interested in what's the פסוק pasuk we learn שטר
shtar from, which is funny, because until now everything had been what's
the source. Presumably, the גמרא Gemara says, maybe you don't need a
פסוק pasuk for שטר shtar because if I am basically writing in
a שטר, shtar, you're free, it's like I am renouncing my claim
to you. It's just I have a legal monetary claim to you
and I'm renouncing it, you don't need a פסוק, pasuk, that's what's
happening. But גמרא Gemara says, but if that's what's happening, why do
you need that in a שטר? shtar? Why can't you have a
verbal renouncing of a claim?
And you could say
but why would you have to say you have to write something
down that works just as well if you just said it? Okay?
Because I'm like right, running on a, whatever it is. Am I
going to be at a place? Don't get to produce the witnesses?
What? Don't get to produce the witnesses?
Just to prove, I, why there might be a benefit to the
slave to have a שטר shtar might be true, but fundamentally it's
not, it's not an act that works by virtue of a שטר.
shtar. It's an act that works just by virtue of the master
renouncing his claim. The שטר shtar whether you prefer a שטר shtar
or don't, that's your choice, but it's not a קנין kinyan of
a שטר. shtar. So why is it, so why is it saying
this? Now, the question is, is that really so obvious to everybody
here that a verbal renouncing of a claim, right, works? So let's
see why the גמרא Gemara assumed that and why the גמרא Gemara
now rejects it. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, it says,
אמר רבא: זאת אומרת עבד עברי גופו קנוי. Amar Rava: Zos omeres
eved Ivri gufo kanui.
This teaches you that even an עבד עברי eved Ivri the body
is considered of possess, purchased, like owned by the master. דהא רב
שמחל על גרעונו, אין גרעונו מחול. De-ha rav she-machal al gir'ono, ein
gir'ono machul. And a master who just wants to be מוחל mochel
on the money owed him, that doesn't work. Now what does this
mean? This is so important because the גמרא Gemara here in two
lines with all this stuff about what פסוק pasuk do you learn
it from, is telling you a very important conceptual question about an
עבד עברי. eved Ivri. I have been emphasizing that an עבד עברי
eved Ivri is not like an עבד כנעני. eved K'naani. You do
not own the body of the עבד עברי. eved Ivri. But there
are still two ways to understand why I am entitled to this
slave's labor, right? One could be it's understood like a type of
a contract and a debt. You owe me a thousand dollars, we've
made a contract that you're going to pay off your debt by
working for me and I am entitled to demand that you work
for me, etc. But fundamentally, it's like a contract, okay? There's another
way of understanding it which might entitle me not just to the,
the contract might entitle me to compel you to work, right, I
mean they have all these like labor laws, right, about like about
but you can imagine that a contract says you're not allowed to
take off, you're compelled to work for me and I'm entitled to
your labor, but fundamentally it's a contract. I have a claim on
you and it's a type of contractual relationship. The other way is
I actually own you, but I own you not as property, I
own you for your labor, למעשה ידיו. li-ma'aseh yadav. Right. So the
model is, let's say I want to buy the fruit of your
tree, okay? So you basically sell me the fruit and then there's
a problem about דבר שלא בא לעולם, davar she-lo ba la-olam, they
don't exist yet, right?
Or do I own your tree? But not that I own it
that I can cut it down, I can own it, the ownership
I have entitles me to the fruit. It doesn't entitle me to
the whole tree, to the whole title of the tree, but it
entitles me to the fruit. And this is the question by עבד
עברי. eved Ivri. Do I own you for your labor, but there's
a sense of ownership, or am I, or are you just obligated
to work for me in a type of contractual relationship? So the
גמרא Gemara is saying is the נפקא מינה, nafka mina, one way
of testing that is: Can I just say forget it, I'm מוחל.
mochel. So if you just have some contractual obligation to me, I
can waive my rights. But if I actually own you, you do
not de-possess yourself of property without actively, without, you can't just say
forget it, I don't care about my car anymore, I waive my
rights to my car. I have to do something, it's not a
waiving of rights. For me to make my car not own my
car, I would either have to sell it to you, or what
I could do is I could be מפקיר mafkir it. So I
could do something verbally, and תוספות Tosfos points out, it is still
possible to do something here verbally without a שטר, shtar, but the
verbal thing would have to be: I renounce ownership of my car,
okay? So that you
could do, תוספות Tosfos says you could do by an עבד עברי.
eved Ivri. I could say: I renounce my ownership of you. But
what I can't do is I can't say I waive my rights,
okay? Waiving my rights doesn't work because it's not just an issue
of rights, it's an issue of ownership. You had a question?
I was just going to say thinking of the parallel to a
husband's relationship to his
wife's properties, you can't m...
Right, and that is, right, that's a classic example of like a
גוף לפירות, guf l'peirot, like he owns it for the fruit. Exactly.
Yes, Charlie.
Get back to the שטר אדמי חבינו כסף, shtar admei chiveinu kesef,
that sounds an awful lot like its securitization of loans that we
do today. That we treat a doc, a loan document, as something
you can sell as if it's real.
Right. But normally הלכה halacha does not treat a שטר חוב shtar
chov as שווה כסף. shaveh kesef.
That's why it's surprising.
I know, so that it's definitely a חידוש chiddush that's גמרא Gemara's
sort of a little glossing over.
Yes. And then the other thing I was going to ask
about כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin. So is a check considered valid as
שווה כסף? shaveh kesef?
No. So again, the answer is no, which makes the גמרא Gemara's
presumption here that a שטר אדמי shtar admei works as כסף kesef
very bizarre, which is why I pointed it out.
So I can, you know, so I can מקדש mekadesh my wife
with say five cents, but I can't write her a check for
ten thousand dollars?
Exactly. Exactly. It has to be שווה כסף shaveh kesef and there's
something like is like is like you know intrinsic value. Exactly. So
it is strange the assumption of this גמרא Gemara but anyway it's
a very important conceptual question by an עבד עברי. eved ivri. So
again, תוספות Tosafot points out it doesn't mean that being מפקיר mafkir
wouldn't work. You could do it verbally. You could say I renounce
my ownership but the גמרא Gemara's question was the שטר, shtar, if
the שטר shtar doesn't say I מפקיר mafkir my ownership. The שטר
shtar says הרי את בן חורין harei at ben chorin which is
effectively saying I waive my rights to you. And that does not
work verbally. Verbally waiving of rights doesn't work because we're talking about
here a real sense of ownership, not just a sense of rights.
But writing in a שטר shtar הרי את בן חורין, harei at
ben chorin, that is seen as a different type of thing as
changing of a status or maybe that then becomes interpreted as also
renouncing ownership and therefore it works. So the interesting idea of this
ברייתא braita that a שטר shtar works, it doesn't have even a
פסוק pasuk to give it a basis of, it just is a
logic logically based on the sense of ownership that you have on
this person so you can renounce that ownership through the שטר. shtar.
But it gets to the heart about whether it's a real a
sense of property ownership or not. Okay, now we go on. Next
line of the משנה. mishna. יתירה עליו אמה עבריה. yeseira alav ama
ivriya. So greater than in another way that somebody a slave a
Hebrew slave gets their freedom,
a girl slave is more than a man because she gets her
freedom by סימנים simanim when she becomes an adult, like she has
pubic hairs and she's you know over 12 years old. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר ריש לקיש אמה עבריה קונה עצמה
במיתת האב מרשות אדון מקל וחומר. amar Reish Lakish ama ivriya kona
atzma b'mitat ha'av meirshat adon m'kal vachomer.
So he has a new one. If the father dies, she gets
free based on a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. What's the קל וחומר?
kal vachomer? ומה סימנים שאין מוציאין מרשות אב, uma simanim she'ein motzi'in
meirshat av,
when she gets סימנים simanim she becomes a נערה, na'ara, she's not
out of the father's control, she's only out of the father's control
when she's a בוגרת. bogeret. A נערה na'ara does not make her
out of the father's control. מוציאין מרשות אדון, motzi'in meirshat adon, but
that's enough to be an adult that gets her out of her
master's control. מיתה שמוציאה מרשות אב, mita shemotzi'a meirshat av, the death
of the father that frees her from the father's control,
אינו דין שמוציאה מרשות אדון? eino din shemotzi'a meirshat adon? How much
more so that that should work to free her? Of course that's
a little absurd because who's the master at the time, right? So
the reason the death of the father gets her out of the
father's control is there's no longer the person who was, you know,
possessing her, who has under who was controlling her. Why that should
work when she's now owned by this master is a little strange,
but that's his קל וחומר. kal vachomer. So now the rest of
today's דף, daf, I mean we're running out of time, but the
whole rest of the next עמוד amud we'll see how far we
get is to try to disprove ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, that the
death of the father does not free this girl who's owned by
the master. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. מיתיבי, meisivei,
I'll ask you on this.
רב הושעיא, Rav Oshaya, Oshaya, רב הושעיא Rav Oshaya asked. We have
a ברייתא, braita, we have the משנה. mishna. It says יתירה עליו
אמה עבריה, yeseira alav ama ivriya, an אמה עבריה ama ivriya has
more ways of freeing herself שקונה עצמה בסימנים. shekona atzma b'simanim. It
says סימנים. simanim. אי איתא, ei isa, and if what you're saying
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is correct, ניתני נמי מיתת האב. nisni nami
mitat ha'av. Say also that the אמה עבריה ama ivriya goes free
with the death of the father. That's also a way in which
she goes free. So the גמרא Gemara says תנא ושייר. tana v'shayer.
Yeah, it's an abbreviated list. It left a few things off. Now
the גמרא, Gemara, that's never a good answer if it only left
one thing off. Okay, if so, the גמרא Gemara always says מאי
שייר דהאי שייר. mai shayer d'hai shayer. You can only say it
left things off if it left something else off as well. You're
not going to give a whole list minus one one thing. So
what else was left off that you could make the claim it's
an incomplete list? שייר מיתת האדון. shayer mitat ha'adon. Ah, it left
off if the master dies. Because if the master dies, well it's
not obvious, okay, because in a case of a normal עבד עברי,
eved ivri, if the master dies he continues to work the six
years for the sons, okay. So that's another way in which she
is different than an עבד עברי. eved ivri. In an עבד עברי
eved ivri the master dies she
works for the sons and by an אמה עבריה ama ivriya she
goes free. So there's two things now left off.
Doesn't the son have to be a ייד Yid potentially or no?
No. If the father dies there's no ייד Yid there at all?
No. The ייד Yid is only when the אדון adon father is
alive. אי משום מיתת האדון, ei mishum mitat ha'adon, the גמרא Gemara
says no, that's not a good example. לאו שיורא הוא. lav shiyura
hu. That was not something that was left off. בקנין בגופו נמי
באיש לא קתני. B'kinyan b'gufo nami b'ish lo kateni. There's a way
in which the death of the master also applies to a case
of a male slave. What's the case? This is an ironic הלכה,
halakha, but when it's an עבד eved is נרצע, nirtza, the ear's
pierced, okay, in that case, the, hold on, let me say, let
me see I'm saying this right, hold on. Shhh, this is the
death of Kohen Gadol. No, no, no, it's not death of Kohen
Gadol, shhh,
it's the death of someone.
Wait, wait,
wait, okay yeah I was right, I was right. In the case,
I was right. Shhh, quiet people. In the case of the נרצע,
nirtza, the הלכה halakha is the guy whose ear was pierced, the
הלכה halakha is, ironically, that even though he's more permanently owned, as
it were, if he dies he does not work for the sons,
okay? So actually you can understand this, let me actually pause for
a moment to make us appreciate because it's very ironic. If the
guy's working six years and the father dies, he continues to work
for the sons. If he did the piercing of the ear and
now he's going to work for I don't know until יובל Yovel
for another 40 years, he doesn't continue to work for the sons.
So the logic is the following, is that when I'm only working
for six years, it's much more like a contract, a contractual relationship.
I have six years of service. So just because the guy dies,
I still owe six years of service, so I continue to pay
it off to the sons. But if I'm a נרצע, nirtza, I'm
much more looked at like property, and therefore דוקא davka I don't
go passed on to the sons, because passed on to the sons,
your property does
pass on to the sons.
That's exactly why it's not, is because the תורה Torah is as
opposed to כנעני Kena'ani is making a point that this person is
not property. Even though he's נרצע nirtza and he's going to work
till the יובל, Yovel, he's still not property, and that's why דוקא
davka doesn't get passed on to the sons. That's the way I
understand it. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says since there's a case
by the man that the man also goes free במיתת האדון, b'misas
ha'adon, so it's not a difference between the woman and the man.
So when the משנה Mishna is mentioning the differences between the woman
and the man, you only have now according to ריש לקיש, Reish
Lakish, why was this case of the death of the father left
off? There's nothing else that was left off. So the גמרא Gemara
says ואלא ניתני? v'ela nistni?
So why didn't they say according to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish the
death of the father? Okay so we have a different answer. Forget
it was an abbreviated list. New answer why it was left off.
תנא דבר שיש לו קצבה קתני דבר שאין לו קצבה לא קתני.
Tana davar she'yesh lo kitzva kateni, davar she'ein lo kitzva lo kateni.
It teaches something that is fixed, not something that's unfixed. Meaning, you
don't know if the father will die, right? When is the father
going to die? Will the father die before the girl becomes an
adult? That you don't know. But the other things you do know.
What are the things you do know? I mean כסף kesef you
always have the right to do כסף kesef and you know how
much כסף. kesef. You know, what was the other things, what way
she comes free? Oh,
six years, יובל, Yovel, those are all things that are predictable and
known, okay? סימנין, simanim, you know, a girl becomes an adult although
the גמרא Gemara is about to question that, but the death of
the father is very up in the air, will that happen, when,
you can't control whether that's going to happen and so on. So
the גמרא Gemara says one minute, והרי סימנין דלית להו קצבה וקתני.
v'harei simanim d'leis lehu kitzva v'kateni. סימנין Simanim you don't know when
the girl will show signs of puberty. So אמר רב ספרא amar
Rav Safra אין להם קצבה למעלה, ein lahem kitzva l'ma'ala, yeah, you
don't know what the upper limit, you know she could be 13
before or 14 before she has those signs. אבל יש להם קצבה
למטה, aval yesh lahem kitzva l'mata, there's a lower limit. You know
it can't happen, you know, before a certain age, okay, before the
age of 12.
So she has to work past 12 then
if she doesn't have pubic hairs. Correct, it's not a question of
age, it's a question of having these physical signs of maturity. דתניא
D'tanya we taught in a ברייתא, braita, בן תשע שנים שהביא שתי
שערות שומא. ben tesha shanim she'hevi shtei se'aros shuma. If a
now here's a ברייתא braita about a boy, but the same idea
would be about a girl. If he's under nine years old and
he has two pubic hairs, then even if those hairs remain till
he becomes 12 or 13 or whatever, they're inconsequential, they're a mole
or something, exactly, they are of no significance. מבן תשע שנים ויום
אחד ועד בן יב שנה ויום אחד, miben tesha shanim v'yom echad
v'ad ben yud-beys shana v'yom echad,
let's say the hairs grow between 9 and 12, and then they
stay on him once he hits 12. This ברייתא braita sounds like
the being in the thirteenth year would count for a boy. ועודן
בו v'oden bo and they're still on him during the thirteenth year,
so according to the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma שומא shuma that's also
inconsequential. The hairs have to grow after he turned 13 or after
he entered his thirteenth year. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר סימן. Rabbi
Yossi b'Rabbi Yehuda omer siman. No, no, no, if they grew even
between the age of 9 and 12 they also count as long
as they're still on him. אם בן יג שנה ויום אחד, im
ben yud-gimmel shana v'yom echad, if they grew once he was 13,
דברי הכל סימן divrei hakol siman everyone says it's a סימן. siman.
Now of course the ברייתא braita is contradictory about whether what's the
story in, you know, during the thirteenth year. It sounded initially that
once he's 12 years and one day he can be an adult,
and then by the end it said only when he's 13 years
and one day. So the גמרא Gemara deals with that, okay, but
the bottom line for us is there is some minimum age by
which the pubic hairs are insignificant, under which the growth is of
pubic hairs. So at least it's more fixed, there's a more sense
of the time when this happens than the idea of the death
of the father. So ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish answer is we're going
to mention puberty because there's at least a general range of time
that happens and we're not going to
mention. So
מתיב רב ששת, mative Rav Sheshet, or we're still going to try
to disprove ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. So Sheshet asks. רבי שמעון אומר,
Rabbi Shimon Omer, ארבעה מעניקים להם. arba'ah ma'anikim lahem. Okay, there are
four scenarios in which you do this הענקה, ha'anakah, you, you know,
laden down the slave who's going free with all of this, all
these gifts, right? הענק תעניק לו. ha'anek ta'anik lo. So four scenarios
you would do it. ג' באיש וג' באשה. gimel b'ish v'gimel b'ishah.
Three you find by a man and three
you find by a woman, meaning, so no, no, no, because there's
overlap. Okay? Meaning... Okay, let's see, Charlie, let's see if you can
figure this one out.
I got it.
איש ish and אשה. ishah. Okay, here's one and one and then
there are two that are shared. Okay, so there are four, three
by man and three by woman. Okay. Okay, ג' באיש
וג' באשה ואי אתה יכול לומר ארבעה באחד.
gimel b'ish
v'gimel b'ishah v'i attah yakhol lomar arba'ah b'echad. Neither
of them has all four. לפי, lefi, which are the ones that
you don't have, you have by one not the other? שאין סימנין
באיש. she'ein simanin b'ish. So the one that works by the אשה
ishah not the איש ish is סימנין. simanin.
Okay, and that you're obviously not going to... and that doesn't have
by the man. שאין סימנין באיש. she'ein simanin b'ish. ואין רציעה באשה.
v'ein retziah b'ishah.
And this is the case of the עבד eved who's the נרצע,
nirtza, and he goes free during the יובל. yovel. Okay, and but
you don't have the case of a נרצע nirtza by a woman.
Okay, it's only by a man. And the two other two we'll
discuss later. But anyway, the point is, the only thing it has
by a woman that it doesn't have by a man is סימנין.
simanin. It doesn't have the death of the father. Okay, so it
says, ואי איתא v'i ita if what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is
saying is correct, ליתני נמי מיתת האב. litni nami mitat ha'av. Mention
also the death of the father. וכי תימא הכא נמי תני ושייר,
v'chi teima hacha nami tani v'shayer, it's an abbreviated list. So besides
the question about what else are we leaving off to make it
abbreviated, והא ארבעה קתני. v'ha arba'ah katani. When it gives a number,
four, and it's obviously clearly trying to enumerate and it sounds like
there's only four ways, it's clear there's not a fifth way. וכי
תימא דבר שיש לו קצבה קתני ודבר שאין לו קצבה לא קתני.
v'chi teima davar she'yesh lo kitzvah katani v'davar she'ein lo kitzvah lo
katani. You'll give the other answer, oh, we're only dealing with things
that have more fixed times in which they occur. והא סימנין דאין
להם קצבה וקתני. v'ha simanin d'ein lahem kitzvah v'katani. But one minute,
סימנין simanin doesn't have a fixed time, וקתני. v'katani. וכי תימא הכא
נמי כדרב ספרא. v'chi teima hacha nami k'deRav Safra. Oh, we have
רב ספרא's Rav Safra answer. It doesn't have a fixed time, an
upper fixed time, but it has a lower fixed time. והאיכא מיתת
האדון דאין להם קצבה וקתני. v'ha'ika mitat ha'adon d'ein lahem kitzvah v'katani.
One minute, one of the things that are in these two, we
don't know what they are, but one of them is מיתת האדון.
mitat ha'adon. Okay,
that works for the girl when the father dies and it works
we said in the case of the נרצע, nirtza, מיתת האדון mitat
ha'adon works. Okay, and maybe we even think... Okay, so that doesn't
have a fixed time. So מיתת האדון mitat ha'adon is mentioned here,
why isn't מיתת האב? mitat ha'av? Okay. והאיכא מיתת האדון דאין להם
קצבה וקתני. v'ha'ika mitat ha'adon d'ein lahem kitzvah v'katani. מיתת האדון נמי
לא קתני. mitat ha'adon nami lo katani.
You know what, מיתת האדון mitat ha'adon isn't in there. Okay. ואלא
ארבעה מאי ניהו. v'ela arba'ah mai nihu. So if that's true, what
are the four? So now we're going to list the four and
we'll show מיתת האדון mitat ha'adon is not. ואלא ארבעה מאי ניהו
שנים ויובל. v'ela arba'ah mai nihu: shanim v'yovel. Okay,
so the two that are shared here is שנים shanim and יובל,
yovel, right?
Six years and the יובל. yovel. Those are the shared. Okay, so
שנים ויובל, shanim v'yovel, ויובל של רציעה. v'yovel shel retziah.
And here is the case of the... the נרצע. nirtza. Oh, I'm
sorry, I put מיתת האדון mitat ha'adon here. The גמרא Gemara first
when it said מיתת האדון mitat ha'adon it thought it was in
the list, thought it was the case of מיתת האדון mitat ha'adon
by the נרצע. nirtza. Remember I told you that in that case
the man also goes free if he's a נרצע nirtza and the
father dies... master dies. So when it said נרצע nirtza by the
איש, ish, it thought it meant מיתת האדון. mitat ha'adon. So it
said, ah, if that's מיתת האדון, mitat ha'adon, you should have מיתת
האב. mitat ha'av. And the answer is no, no, no, that's not
the case of נרצע. nirtza. The case of נרצע nirtza going free
is when the יובל yovel hits the נרצע. nirtza. So this is
a יובל yovel during the six years and this is a יובל
yovel of the נרצע. nirtza. Okay, but מיתת האדון mitat ha'adon is
not in this list. And we're explaining that the reason מיתת האב
mitat ha'av is not and מיתת האדון mitat ha'adon is not is
אין לו קצבה. ein lo kitzvah. So we've defended ריש לקיש, Reish
Lakish, there's a reason מיתת האב mitat ha'av is not in this
list.
Okay. שנים ויובל ויובל של רציעה ואמה העבריה בסימנין. shanim v'yovel v'yovel
shel retziah v'amah ha'ivriyah b'simanin. הכי נמי מסתברא. hacha nami mistabra. It
makes sense that those are the four being referred to. דקתני סיפא
אי אתה יכול לומר ארבעה באחד מהם. d'katani seifa i attah yakhol
lomar arba'ah b'echad mehem. לפי שאין סימנין באיש ואין רציעה באשה. lefi
she'ein simanin b'ish v'ein retziah b'ishah. Okay, so you can't say four
because neither one of them has all four. ואי איתא ביה אמיא
משכחת לה ארבעה. v'i ita beiah amaya mashkachat lah arba'ah. But if
it were true that we were actually talking about... if this was
talking not about יובל, yovel, but if this was talking about מיתת
האדון, mitat ha'adon, right? That's what we thought initially, that the נרצע
nirtza was מיתת האדון. mitat ha'adon. It says, that's not true that
that's only by the איש, ish, because מיתת האדון mitat ha'adon also
works by the אשה. ishah. So clearly מיתת האדון mitat ha'adon is
not here, because if מיתת האדון mitat ha'adon were here, it would
be true both by the איש ish and the אשה. ishah. So
it must be the case of נרצע nirtza is the יובל yovel
of the נרצע, nirtza, and this is a יובל yovel during the
six, and we don't have מיתת האדון mitat ha'adon because that's not
a fixed time. It's not predictable, and if we don't have מיתת
אדון, misas adon, it also explains why we don't have מיתת האב.
misas ha'av. So we've been able to defend ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
why מיתת האב misas ha'av is not on that list. Okay. שמע
מינה. Shma mina. Okay, so we'll end with that, but we're going
to continue tomorrow to see if we can manage to disprove ריש
לקיש. Reish Lakish.
So suppose for קידושין, kiddushin, so he gives her a dollar bill,
right? Yeah. A dollar bill isn't really intrinsically valuable either.
Yeah, there is a good question whether a dollar bill is really.